<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe catechisme containing the summe of the Gospell of Iesus Christ, and his life, declared more at large by the foure euangelists, Mathew, Marke, Luke, and Iohn / written by Edmund Littleton, of Sittingborne in Kent, preacher.</title>
            <author>Littleton, Edmund.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15717.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2196</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23121751</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23121751</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26272</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26272)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1798:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe catechisme containing the summe of the Gospell of Iesus Christ, and his life, declared more at large by the foure euangelists, Mathew, Marke, Luke, and Iohn / written by Edmund Littleton, of Sittingborne in Kent, preacher.</title>
                  <author>Littleton, Edmund.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Purslouue, for Simon Stafford,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸(-A1).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26272:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26272:1"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE CATE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, containing the <hi>Summe of the
Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and his life, declared more at large by the
foure Euangeliſts, <hi>Mathew, Marke, Luke and Iohn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by Edmund Littleton, of <hi>Sittingborne</hi> in KENT,
Preacher.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Teach a child in the trade of his way, and when hee is olde, hee
ſhall not depart from it,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro. 22.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>This is life eternall, that they know thee the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true God,
and whom thou hast ſent, Ieſus Chriſt,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn 17.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by GEORGE PVRSLOVVE for <hi>Simon Stafford.</hi>
1616.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:26272:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26272:2"/>
            <head>A briefe Catechiſme, contayning the Summe of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<hi>of our bleſſed LORD and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, ſet downe</hi> more
at large by the foure Euangeliſts.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> 
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is the Goſpell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is the glad tidings of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, brought
vnto vs by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth the Goſpell principally containe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Goſpell doth principally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine theſe
foure parts, to wit:</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> The birth of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The life of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> The death of Chriſt, and</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> His reſurrection.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What doe you comprehend vnder the title of his
birth?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26272:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Vnder the title of his birth, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend his
pedigrée, as hee is man; and alſo his generation, as hee is God,
begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his Father before al worlds, <hi>Iohn. 1.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, his Conception of the virgin <hi>Mary, Luke.
1.31.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Where was Chriſt borne?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> At <hi>Beth-lehem</hi> in the land of
<hi>Iudah,</hi> as it was before prophecied, <hi>Mica. 5.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. When was Chriſt borne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When the Kingdome was taken from the royall tribe of
<hi>Iuda,</hi> as <hi>Iacob</hi> the Patriark on his death-bed foretold,
<hi>Gen. 49.10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What circumſtances were incident to the birth of
Chriſt?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Three moſt excellent and notable aboue the
reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Which were they?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1</hi> The moſt ioyfull ſong of the Angels, that gaue
witneſſe to his birth, <hi>Luke 2.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> The viſitation of the ſheepe-heards,
<hi>Verſe 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> The comming of the Wiſe men, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26272:3"/>their homage don vnto him, <hi>Mat.
2.1.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Who doe make mention of theſe things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thrée of the holy Euangeliſts, that is,
<hi>Mathew, Luke,</hi> and <hi>Iohn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Now for the life of Chriſt, I pray you tell me what
he did, before he took his publike function vpon him?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Before he tooke vpon him the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of
his publike function, Firſt, he fled into Egypt, <hi>Mat. 2.13, 14</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, hee was obedient to his ſuppoſed father, and to
the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> his mother, <hi>Luke 2.51.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thirdly, he frequented the holy exerciſes of religion in
the Temple, &amp; there diſputed with the Doctors of the lawe, <hi>Verſe
43.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Who do report this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. Mathew</hi> maketh mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the firſt, and
<hi>Luke</hi> of the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. I would gladly know of you, after what manner he was
eſtabliſhed in his office, and how he liued after he was called
thereunto?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His calling was confirmed vnto
<pb facs="tcp:26272:4"/>him by three notable teſtimonies:
as,</p>
            <p>Firſt, by his baptiſme, wherein the Father and the holy
Ghoſt approued him, <hi>Mat. 3.16, 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by his conqueſt ouer the deuill, tempting him in the
deſert.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, by the faithfull witneſſe of <hi>Iohn</hi> the
Baptiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Who doe make mention of this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All the foure Euangeliſts, <hi>Mat. 3.14. Mar.
1.9. Luk. 3.21. Ioh. 1.6, 7. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What did hee in the time of his calling, to wit, for
thoſe three yeeres and 6. moneths, in which he was conuerſant in diuers
places, amongſt the Iewes, as in Galile, Samaria, and Iudea?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He did teach the doctrine of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and
confirmed the ſame by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of miracles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What do you learn by the doctrine that hee
taught?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I do eſpecially learne two things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, who is the true Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the benefits that are to be obtained by him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26272:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What doth the doctrine of Chriſt
containe?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt containeth and
truely teacheth vs the matter of our faith, or Chriſt himſelfe: that is to
ſay, both who he is, &amp; what a one hee is to vs, to wit, a Sauiour,
<hi>Mat. 1.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And what elſe?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That he is perfit God, &amp; perfit man, and alſo
the meanes how he is to be apprehended of vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>How may wee apprehend Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Onely by Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What benefits get we by Chriſt thus
apprehended?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By Ieſus Chriſt thus apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a true and
liuely faith, we obtain theſe benefits following: viz.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, our <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> which is, to be
accounted perfitly righteous in the ſight of God.</item>
               <item>Secondly, our <hi>Sanctification,</hi> which is, the
reſtauration of the integrity of our nature loſt by <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:26272:5"/>
               <item>Thirdly, our <hi>Glorification,</hi> which is, to be made
heires and citizens of the kingdome of heauen.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And to conclude, that comfortable Charity wherewith we loue both
God and our neighbour; and all the good fruits that come thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> But I pray you tell mee, how is this doctrine
confirmed vnto vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the right vſe of the two Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,
Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In the miracles of Chriſt, what haue we
chiefly to conſider?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the miracles of Ieſus Chriſt, we haue
eſpecially to conſider his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine power in the working of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why, how did Chriſt worke his
miracles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Sometime by outward applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of meanes, as by
touching thoſe whom he healed, <hi>Iohn 9.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometime by his word onely, <hi>Iohn 5.8, 9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſometime by his diuine power without eyther, <hi>Mat.
9.20, 21, 22.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26272:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What things do you containe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the title of
his death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, a preparation to the ſtory of his death,
wherein theſe things are chiefly to be conſidered, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The apprehending of Chriſt by the Souldiers, <hi>Mat.
26.47.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The treaſon of <hi>Iudas Iſcariot, Verſ. 48.49.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The outragious violence of the Souldiers, <hi>Verſe
50.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the proceſſe, or declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the cauſe, for
the which hee was condemned:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, of the Iewes, <hi>Mat. 26.65, 66.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, of <hi>Pilate,</hi> at their impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunacy, in the
preſence of <hi>Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiaphas, Luke 23.22, 23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And thirdly, the ſtrife between <hi>Pilate</hi> and the
Iewes in the iudgement hall.</item>
               <item>Fourthly, and laſtly, the bringing of him before
<hi>Herod,</hi> &amp; the auouching of his innocency by the teſtimony of the
Iudge himſelfe, <hi>Luke 23.14, 15.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What did they to Chriſt before his
condemnation?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26272:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1</hi> They did buffet him, <hi>Mat. 26.67.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> They beat him with ſtaues, <hi>Mat.
27.30.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> They ſcorned him, <hi>Mat. 26.68.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> They ſpat in his face, <hi>Mat.
26.67.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> They crowned him with thorns, and clothed him
with purple, in deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> And to conclude, moſt vnworthily they did
whip him, <hi>Mar. 15.15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What followeth next?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſentence of condemnation, and the execution
thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What haue we to conſider therein?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1</hi> The moſt lamentable kind of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment that
he was put to.</p>
            <p>In body, the moſt painefull &amp; ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full death of the
Croſſe, <hi>Mark. 15.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſoule, the moſt extreme torments of hell, <hi>Verſ.
34.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> The moſt vile reproch done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, in
forcing him to beare his owne Croſſe towardes the place of execution: and
there, in matching him betwéen two arrant theeues; where
<pb facs="tcp:26272:6"/>the Iewes taunt him, and ſcorne
him, and in bitter deſpight, entitle him <hi>King of the Iewes, Mat.
27.37.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Where was Chriſt put to death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In a noyſome and and filthy place without the
towne gates, called <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotha, Mat. 27.33.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What miracles were ſhewed at his
death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Diuers, and thoſe very ſtrange and
wonderfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What were they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſunne was darkened for the ſpace of three
whole houres ouer all the land, <hi>Mat. 27.45.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> The vayle of the Temple rent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder from
the top to the bottome.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> The earth did quake, <hi>Verſe 51.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> The rockes cleft aſunder, and</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> The graues did open, <hi>Verſe 52.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What became of the body of Chriſt after his
death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It was buried in a garden, by two honourable
Counſellers, <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and <hi>Nicodemus, Ioh. 19.38, 39,
41.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth the fourth and laſt <pb facs="tcp:26272:7"/>part
of the Goſpell containe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His reſurrection the third day, according to his
promiſe, <hi>Mat. 28.6. &amp; 20.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein we are to conſider:</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> The gard of Souldiers that wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the
ſepulcher.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The wonderfull riſing of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy out of the
ſepulcher, <hi>Mat. 27.66. &amp; 28.2. &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhereby are thoſe things proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and confirmed vnto
vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, by the teſtimony of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, <hi>Mat.
28.6. Ioh. 20.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by the confeſſion of the ſouldiers to the high
Prieſts. <hi>Mat. 28.11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, by the ſight and féeling of the
Apoſtles and many others, <hi>Ioh. 20.27, 28. 1. Cor. 15.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How long was Chriſt on the earth after his
Reſurrection?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſpace of <hi>40.</hi> dayes, &amp; then he
aſcended vp into heauen, <hi>Acts. 1.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat doth he there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He is there reſident on the right
<pb facs="tcp:26272:7"/>hand of God his Father, making
inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for vs, and from thence ſhall come at the laſt day, to
iudge both the quicke and the dead.</p>
            <trailer>And this is briefly the Summe of the whole Goſpell,
deſcribed more at large by the foure Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, <hi>Mathew, Marke,
Luke,</hi> and <hi>Iohn.</hi>
            </trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
